https://library.wayne.edu/info/about/policies/privacy.php

Select libraries are now open to Wayne State students, faculty and staff. See what services we're offering online and in person
Wayne State University
Undergraduate Library
8:00am - 9:00pm
Arthur Neef Law Library 8:30am - 5:00pmPurdy/Kresge Library Closed to the PublicReuther Library By AppointmentShiffman Medical Library 8:30am - 5:00pmUndergraduate Library 8:00am - 9:00pm
All Library Calendars
Wayne State University
Hours
Arthur Neef Law Library8:30am - 5:00pmPurdy/Kresge LibraryClosed to the PublicReuther LibraryBy AppointmentShiffman Medical Library8:30am - 5:00pmUndergraduate Library8:00am - 9:00pm
All Library Calendars
Quicklinks
Article Databases
Catalog
eJournals
Google Scholar
Interlibrary Services
Research Guides
Sign In
WSU LoginAcademica, Canvas, Email, etc.
My Library AccountRenew Books, Request Material, etc.
Make a Gift
back to Wayne.edu
Get face-to-face reference help on Zoom!
Have a difficult research project? Jump on Zoom reference to chat live and get the help you need!
Zoom with us now
December's Subject of the Month
French Detroit
Image from the William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
Read More
Reserve space or a computer at the libraries
Make a reservation to use the Undergraduate, Shiffman or Law Libraries
Reserve your spot now!
Interlibrary Services are back!
Pickup items that you've requested through our catalog, ILL or Mel at the UGL
Learn more
Service interruptions during holiday break
Follow the link for a list of service changes during the holiday closure.
Read More
Wayne State University
Skip to Quicklinks
Skip to Sitemap
Skip to Main Navigation
Skip to News
Menu
Resources
Sign In
WSU LoginAcademica, Canvas, Email, etc.
My Library AccountRenew Books, Request Material, etc.
Help
Chat
Email
Call
Text
FAQ
Staff Directory
Make Appointment
Sign In
Wayne State Login
Academica, Canvas, Email, etc.
My Library Account
Renew Books, Request Material, etc.
Article Databases
Catalog
eJournals
Google Scholar
Interlibrary Services
Research Guides
Reservations & Pickup
Staff Directory
Introduction
Privacy is essential to the exercise of free speech, free thought, and free association.  In this library the right to privacy is the right to open inquiry without having the subject of one’s interest examined or scrutinized by others.  Confidentiality exists when a library is in possession of personally identifiable information about users and keeps that information private on their behalf.
The courts have upheld the right to privacy based on the Bill of Rights of the U.S. Constitution.  Citizens of the state of Michigan are protected by Chapter 397 of the Michigan Compiled Laws, Library Privacy Act. This library's privacy and confidentiality policies are in compliance with applicable federal, state, and local laws.
Our commitment to your privacy and confidentiality has deep roots not only in law but also in the ethics and practices of librarianship.  In accordance with the American Library Association’s Code of Ethics: “We protect each library user’s right to privacy and confidentiality with respect to information sought or received and resources consulted, borrowed, acquired, or transmitted.”
Wayne State University Libraries’ Commitment to Our Users Rights of Privacy and Confidentiality
This privacy policy explains your privacy and confidentiality rights, the steps this library takes to respect and protect your privacy when you use library resources, and how we deal with personally identifiable information that we may collect from our users.
1.  Notice & Openness
Library users have the right of “notice” -- to be informed about the policies governing the amount and retention of personally identifiable information, and about why that information is necessary for the provision of library services.
We post publicly and acknowledge openly the privacy and information-gathering policies of this library.  Whenever policies change, notice of those changes is disseminated widely to our users.
In all cases we avoid creating unnecessary records, we avoid retaining records not needed for the fulfillment of the mission of the library, and we do not engage in practices that might place information on public view.
Information we may gather and retain about current and valid library users include the following
User Registration Information
Circulation Information
Interlibrary Loan and Document Delivery contact information
Electronic Access Information
Information Required to Provide Library Services
2.  Choice & Consent
This policy explains our information practices and the choices you can make about the way the library collects and uses your information.  We will not collect or retain your private and personally identifiable information without your consent.  Further, if you consent to give us your personally identifiable information, we will keep it confidential and will not sell, license or disclose personal information to any third party without your consent, unless we are compelled to do so under the law or to comply with a court order.
If you wish to receive borrowing or interlibrary loan privileges, we must obtain certain information about you in order to provide you with a library account. If you are affiliated with Wayne State University, the library automatically receives personally identifiable information to create and update your library account from the Registrar's Office (for students) or Human Resources (for employees).
When visiting our library’s web site and using our electronic services, you may choose or be asked to provide your name, e-mail address, library card barcode, phone number or home address.
We never use or share the personally identifiable information provided to us online in ways unrelated to the ones described above without also providing you an opportunity to prohibit such unrelated uses, unless we are compelled to do so under the law or to comply with a court order.
3.  Access by Users
Individuals who use library services that require the use of personally identifiable information are entitled to view and update their information. You may view your personal information online or in person and request that it be updated if it is not correct.  In both instances, you may be asked to provide some sort of verification of identity.
The purpose of accessing and updating your personally identifiable information is to ensure that library operations can function properly.  Such functions may include notification of overdue items, recalls, reminders, etc.  The library will explain the process of accessing or updating your information so that all personally identifiable information is accurate and up to date.
4. Data Integrity & Security
Lecture Capture
The Library System is responsible for classroom technology design and support in General Purpose Classrooms, and began recording lectures upon faculty request in 2001. Lectures are recorded only when a faculty member requests this service and are published in Blackboard for the use of the students in their course. Other release of the recordings is done only by 1) request of the faculty member, 2) court order, or 3) subpoena. The privacy, confidentiality and intellectual freedom provisions of this policy apply to lecture recordings made for WSU faculty by the Library System.
Data Integrity
The data we collect and maintain at the library must be accurate and secure.  We take reasonable steps to assure data integrity, including: using only reputable sources of data; providing our users access to their own personally identifiable data; updating data whenever possible; utilizing middleware authentication systems that authorize use without requiring personally identifiable information; destroying untimely data or converting it to anonymous form.
Data Retention
We protect personally identifiable information from unauthorized disclosure once it is no longer needed to manage library services. Information that should be regularly purged or shredded includes personally identifiable information on library resource use, material circulation history, and security/surveillance tapes and logs.
Tracking Users
We remove links between patron records and materials borrowed when items are returned and we delete records as soon as the original purpose for data collection has been satisfied.  We permit in-house access to information in all formats without creating a data trail.  Our library has invested in appropriate technology to protect the security of any personally identifiable information while it is in the library’s custody, and we ensure that aggregate, summary data is stripped of personally identifiable information.  We do not ask library visitors or web site users to identify themselves or reveal any personal information unless they are borrowing materials, requesting special services, registering for programs or classes, or making remote use from outside the library of those portions of the Library's web site restricted to registered borrowers under license agreements or other special arrangements.  We discourage users from choosing passwords or PINs that could reveal their identity, including social security numbers.  We regularly remove cookies, web history, cached files, or other computer and Internet use records and other software code that is placed on our computers or networks.
Third Party Security
We ensure that our library’s contracts and licenses reflect our policies and legal obligations concerning user privacy and confidentiality.  Should a third party require access to our users’ personally identifiable information, our agreements address appropriate restrictions on the use, aggregation, dissemination, and sale of that information, particularly information about minors.  In circumstances in which there is a risk that personally identifiable information may be disclosed, we will warn our users.  When connecting to licensed databases outside the library, we release only information that authenticates users as "members of our community."   Nevertheless, we advise users of the limits to library privacy protection when accessing remote sites
Cookies
Users of networked computers will need to enable cookies in order to access a number of resources available through the library.  A cookie is a small file sent to the browser by a Web site each time that site is visited.  Cookies are stored on the user's computer and can potentially transmit personal information.  Cookies are often used to remember information about preferences and pages visited. You can refuse to accept cookies, can disable cookies, and remove cookies from your hard drive.  Our Library servers use cookies solely to verify that a person is an authorized user in order to allow access to licensed library resources and to customize Web pages to that user's specification. Cookies sent by our Library servers will disappear when the user's computer browser is closed.  We will not share cookies information with external third parties.
Security Measures
Our security measures involve both managerial and technical policies and procedures to protect against loss and the unauthorized access, destruction, use, or disclosure of the data.  Our managerial measures include internal organizational procedures that limit access to data and ensure that those individuals with access do not utilize the data for unauthorized purposes.  Our technical security measures to prevent unauthorized access include encryption in the transmission and storage of data; limits on access through use of passwords; and storage of data on secure servers or computers that are inaccessible from a modem or network connection.
Staff access to personal data
We permit only authorized Library staff with assigned confidential passwords to access personal data stored in the Library’s computer system for the purpose of performing library work. We will not disclose any personal data we collect from you to any other party except where required by law or to fulfill an individual user's service request. The Library does not sell or lease users' personal information to companies, universities, or individuals.
5.  Enforcement & Redress
Our library will not share data on individuals with third parties unless required by law.  We conduct regular privacy audits in order to ensure that all library programs and services are enforcing our privacy policy.  Library users who have questions, concerns, or complaints about the library’s handling of their privacy and confidentiality rights should file written comments with the Dean of the Library System.  We will respond in a timely manner and may conduct a privacy investigation or review of policy and procedures.
We authorize only the Dean and/or her designee to receive or comply with requests from law enforcement officers; we confer with our legal counsel whenever possible before determining the proper response.  We will not make library records available to any agency of state, federal, or local government unless a subpoena, warrant, court order or other investigatory document is issued by a court of competent jurisdiction that shows good cause and is in proper form.  We have trained all library staff and volunteers to refer any law enforcement inquiries to library administrators.
Table of Contents
Resources
Article Databases
Catalog
Citation Linker
Digital Collections
Digital Commons
eJournals
WSU LoginAcademica, Canvas, Email, etc.
My Library AccountRenew Books, Request Material, etc.
